玄黄端现 太极混沌如鸡蛋
ln the beginning, there was darkness...
随着轰的一声
and then, bang...
诞生了无限膨胀的
giving birth to an endless expanding existence...
时间 空间和物质
of time, space, and matter.
现在所见超乎我们的想象
Now, see further than we've ever imagined...
超越了客观认知极限
beyond the limits of our existence...
那地方我们称之为"宇宙"
in a place we call "The Universe."
我们所知的万物 时间 空间 物质
Everything that we know, time, space, and matter...
都将在劫难逃
are doomed.
依赖阳光生存的所有生命都将很快灭绝
Any life that depends on sunlight will rapidly go extinct...
因为维系生命的能源越发稀少
as there are fewer sources of life-providing energy.
无论是炼狱里的世界末日
Whether by the Armageddon of an inferno...
还是困于冰魔之爪
or in the grip of an icy executioner...
宇宙本身将命丧冻结 所有生命无一幸免
The universe itselfwill freeze to death and all life with it.
乃至深太空里无形的力量
Or even by an unseen force from the depths of space.
确确实实 每一个粒子 每一个原子
And literally every particle, every atom...
宇宙间的每一个结构都将爆发
every structure in the universe would explode.
坐稳了 马上进入[宇宙末日]了
Beware, here comes the "CosmicApocalypse."
--==本影片由 CMCT 团队 荣誉出品==--
更多精彩影视 请访问 http://cmct.cc
影片压制:春树  字幕来源:五羊皮  调校:御雪寒狼  招募Q号:76846146
[历史频道] 第二季 第十八集 宇宙末日
[History Channel] The UniverseⅡ 18of19 Cosmic.Apocalypse
公元200亿年
The year is 20 billion A.D...
宇宙出现了严重的错误
and there is something gravely wrong with the universe.
自从爆炸诞生以来 宇宙一直在膨胀
Ever since its explosive birth, the universe has been expanding...
不断长大 永不见底
growing ceaselessly into an infinite unknown.
然而 在遥远未来的一天
However, on this day in the distant future...
仰望星空
looking up at the sky...
四面八方的星系发生了逆转
galaxies from all directions have reversed course...
加速奔向我们的银河系
and are speeding towards our own Milky Way.
灾难带来万世之劫
The catastrophic implication is fatal.
宇宙在塌缩
The universe is collapsing...
我们所知的万物将终结于斯
and everything we know will cease to be.
生命在劫难逃了
Life is doomed.
我们看到其它星系
When we look at other galaxies...
看到它们在磕磕碰碰中直奔我们而来
we'll see them coming in toward us on a collision course.
突然 我们看到行星从四面八方奔来
All of a sudden, we see stars coming at us from all directions.
所有星系开始碰撞
All the galaxies will start colliding...
里面的恒星碰撞在一起
and the stars within them will get crunched together.
恒星相撞 行星相撞
The stars will collide, the planets will collide.
行星将被恒星吞没
Planets will get swallowed by stars.
突然之间 温度升高了
All of a sudden, temperatures begin to rise.
突然之间 海洋沸腾了
All of a sudden, the oceans boil.
突然之间 山体熔化了
All of a sudden, the mountains will melt.
噢 天哪 简直乱套了
Oh, man, it's going to be chaos.
一片混乱
lt's going to be pandemonium.
宇宙的温度开始飙升了
And the universe itself begins to reach blistering temperatures.
所有的智能生命早已丧命 因为我们全都命葬火海了
All intelligent life must die because we'll all be incinerated.
宇宙在巨响中终结于一个火球
The universe ends with a bang, in a cosmic fireball.
这是启示录的景象
This is the vision of the Apocalypse...
源自大塌缩理论
according to a theory known as the Big Crunch.
大塌缩脚本里的情景
What's happening with the Big Crunch scenario...
就是宇宙间所有的物质
is that all of the matter in the universe...
所有的能量 星系 恒星
and all the energy, the galaxies, the stars in them...
将通通移回原位
are all moving back towards each other...
宇宙塌缩了
and the universe is shrinking.
物体将越靠越近
Things are getting closer and closer together.
现在的宇宙 刚好相反 在膨胀
Our universe right now, on the other hand, is expanding.
每天都在增加空间
Each day, there is more and more space...
星系分得越来越开
as galaxies get further and further apart.
大塌缩期间的情况刚好相反
The opposite happens during the Big Crunch.
物体之间的空间在压缩
The space between things is shrinking...
就好像这廊道里挤满了人
and that's rather like filling up this hallwaywith people...
人越来越多
and there are more and more people.
人们之间的空间变得越来越小
The space between them, then, is getting smaller and smaller.
他们摩肩接踵
They bump into each other...
他们努力相互闪避
they're trying to dodge out of each other"s way...
于是 所有的东西都在升温 能量越来越大
and so everything is heating up. and getting more and more energetic...
越来越多的情况发生在了这个不大的空间里
as more and more things happen in this small space.
同样的情况就发生在大塌缩的情景中
Exactly the same thing would happen in the Big Crunch scenario...
构成万物的各种粒子
where various particles that make everything up...
彼此相碰越发频繁
are bumping into each other more frequently.
星系与恒星在相互靠近时
The galaxies and the stars...
开始碰撞
as they're getting closer to each other...start distorting each other...
因而整个开始升温
and so the whole thing's beginning to heat up...
就像人满为患的房间里温度会升高一样
just like a crowded room would heat up.
这个过程会持续下去
The process continues...
随着宇宙的温度变得越来越高
with the temperature of the universe getting higher and higher...
乃至原子本身开始土崩瓦解
to the point that the atoms themselves begin to fall apart.
最终 我们广袤的宇宙会垮塌成一个微点
Finally, ourvast universe collapses...into a microscopic point.
我们将终结于物质汤羹
We'll end up with this soup of matter...
其作料是基本粒子
which is made offundamental particles...
在高能 高温下不停地搅和
which are milling around at high energy, high temperature.
我们所知的生命一网打尽
Life as we know it has no escape.
然而 宇宙或许最终不会点燃熊熊的地狱之火
However, the universe may not ultimately ignite...into an all-consuming hellfire.
对于世界末日有两种剧基本的说法
There are two basic paradigms for the end ofthe world.
第一个 宇宙将终结于大火
First, the universe is going to end in fire.
那是基督教的世界末日理论
That's the Christian theory ofArmageddon...
大火和硫磺 依次出现
fire and brimstone and the second coming.
然而挪威人也有自己的传说
But the Norse also had their legends.
他们有毁灭之日的传说 诸神之黄昏
They had the legend of Ragnarok, Twilight ofthe Gods...
称 会有可怕的暴风雪
where there would be this monstrous snowstorm...
吞噬整个宇宙
that would engulf the entire universe.
天堂里会有一场恶战
There would be this great battle in heaven...
甚至奥丁神(战神) 托尔神(雷神)以及各路神灵
and even Odin and even Thor and all the great gods...
都会逐个慢慢死去
would slowly die one by one...
我们都将死于大冻结
and we would all die in a great freeze...
甚至连神灵都通通死翘翘
when even the gods themselves are frozen.
尽管大塌缩符合基督教版本的世界末日
Whereas the Big Crunch fits the Christian vision of the end of days...
然而科学界也有不同的理论
science also has a different theory...
即有可能是终结于冰冻
that it may instead all end in ice.
最终 取决于宇宙膨胀的势头
Ultimately, it depends on whether the momentum...of the expansion of the universe...
能否克服引起塌缩的引力
can overcome the collapsing attraction of gravity.
想象一下 球拍与球接触的瞬间
lmagine that the moment of contact between bat and ball...
就是大爆炸的初始爆发
is the initial explosion ofthe Big Bang.
所有东西被喷发出去
Everything's being thrown outward...
问题是 它是会自己重新塌缩
and the issue is, will it re-collapse upon itself...
还是会继续膨胀呢？
orwill it continue to expand?
这两种可能性同时存在
And those two possibilities are very similar...
一旦你将球打出去后
to what happens when you launch a ball into the air.
如果我往高处打 重力相对击打瞬间的力量
lf l launch it upwards, and if gravity is strong enough...
足够大话
compared to how much energy l put into that initial launch...
重力就会将球拉回来
it'll pull it back down...
这就像宇宙膨胀一段时间后
and that's like the universe expanding out for a while...
又折腾回来了
and then crunching back in.
不过大塌缩并不一定是一切的终结
But the Big Crunch doesn't have to be the end of everything.
如果宇宙塌缩
lf the universe collapses...
有可能随之而来的是又一次大爆炸
what might subsequently follow is another Big Bang...
又一轮膨胀
another expansion event...
有可能膨胀一段时间后再次塌缩
and that might expand for a while and then re-collapse.
所以你可以想象那种可能性
So you can imagine the possibility...
实际上宇宙就是在循环
that actually the universe isjust cyclic...
膨胀 收缩
and so it expands...and then contracts.
每一次弹跳都是又一次大爆炸
Each bounce is another Big Bang.
然而是否就不存在足够的引力来掌控宇宙呢？
But what if there isn't enough gravity to rein in the universe?
我用足够的力道将其击打出去
l launch it upwards with enough energy...
它就完全逃逸了
that it completely escapes.
宇宙间没有足够的质量让其重新塌缩
There's not enough mass in the universe...
那样它就会一路膨胀下去
to make it re-collapse, and so it continues to expand.
最终 尽管这种膨胀会放缓脚步
Eventually, though this expansion ought to slow...
但是骇人的是 科学观察揭示的是迥然不同的情况
shockingly, scientific observations reveal something completely different.
膨胀正变得越来越快
lt's getting faster.
宇宙貌似脱缰之马
The universe seems to be careening out of control.
膨胀在加速 它在再次发飙
This expansion is accelerating. lt's kicking in once again.
我们正经历着暴涨式扩张
We are undergoing an inflationary expansion.
所以我们现在知道的宇宙正在膨胀
So the universe we now know is expanding...
其额外的加速超乎你的想象
with this extra acceleration...that is beyond what you would have thought...
完全要归咎于初始爆炸
wasjust due to the initial explosion.
不光是球逃逸了
Not only does the ball escape...
而且好像是球上装了一个小火箭引擎
but it's as though a little rocket engine was on the ball...
它在加速远离地球 越来越快
and it accelerates away from the Earth even faster.
这种可能性真是有点始料未及的
This is a possibility that was somewhat unexpected.
宇宙空间的容量
The volume of space in the universe...
看似注定增大无止境
seems destined to increase forever.
这就意味着遥远的星系
What this means is that distant galaxies...
会快速远离我们
are going to go zooming away from us...
最终会离开视野
and will eventually become invisible...
因为它们会远到难以发现
because they'll be too far away to see.
看不到星系彼此快速远离
And without seeing galaxies rushing away from each other...
未来的文明将会失去所有的历史感
future civilizations will lose all sense of history.
他们不会知道曾经有过大爆炸
They won't know that there was ever a Big Bang.
因此 你会觉得宇宙间唯一的结构就是银河系
So you will think that the only structure...within the universe is the Milky Way galaxy...
宇宙的其余部分
and that the rest of the universe...
就是一片空白 没有星星
is effectively empty, devoid of stars.
另一个科学理论主张
Another scientific theory proposes...
这种膨胀会越发加快
that this expansion will balloon even faster.
一旦出现这种情况 残酷的末日就会降临我们的宇宙
lfthis does happen, a violent end awaits our cosmos.
假设可恶的能量在单位时间里加大
Suppose the amount of repulsive energy...increases with time per unit volume.
最终将会增强到引起星系团分崩离析
lt'll eventually grow strong enough...to cause clusters of galaxies to get ripped apart...
随后星系本身也将土崩瓦解
and then galaxies themselves will get ripped apart.
恒星将开始相互远离
The stars will start flying away from one another...
不再靠引力彼此拴住
no longer held together by gravity...
于是行星系 如我们的太阳系
and then planetary systems like our solar system...
也将分崩离析
will get ripped apart...
于是恒星 行星都将分崩离析
and then stars and planets will get ripped apart...
于是人类也将分崩离析
and then humans will get ripped apart...
于是构成我们的每个原子也将分崩离析
and then the very atoms ofwhich we are made will get ripped apart.
这被称为大撕裂 那真是毛骨悚然的情况
That's called the Big Rip, and it's a really scary possibility.
不过请别担心
But don't worry.
我们多数人并不认为会发生那样的情况
Most of us don't think it's going to happen.
但是 即使膨胀的速度永远不会到达那个临界点
But even ifthe rate of expansion never reaches this tipping point...
我们宇宙的未来依然前程未卜
the future of our universe still isn't promising.
其温度会降低
lts temperature decreases.
会变得越来越冷 越来越暗
lt's getting colder and colder and darker and darker...
因为微弱的星光将会照射更大的空间
because the feeble light emitted by stars...is going into a progressively larger volume...
因而宇宙将会变得极其寒冷 极其黑暗
so the universe is going to get really cold and really dark.
基本上是个阴森之地
Basically, a pretty gloomy place.
宇宙本身 我们现在认为
The universe itself, we now believe...
将会死于冰 而非死于火
will die in ice, rather than fire.
我们认为宇宙将会死于大冻结
We think the universe will die in a great freeze...
就像挪威传说预言的那样
just like the Norse legends foretell...
而非这个大塌缩里的世界末日
rather than this Armageddon of a Big Crunch.
如果宇宙坚持目前的进程
lf the universe continues on its present course...
我们将注定有一个宇宙冰河时代 阳光将会熄灭
we're destined for a cosmic ice age where sunlight itself goes extinct.
到了公元100万亿年
By the year 100 trillion A.D...
一息尚存的人类文明
the last remnants of human civilization...
有可能被迫蜗居在我们星系的这个偏远的黑暗角落里
may be forced to settle here in this distant dark corner of our galaxy.
它们蜷缩在最后尚在燃烧的恒星旁
They'll be huddled around the last burning star in the sky...
然而悲哀的是 它很快也将寿终正寝
but, sadly, it too will soon die.
我们的银河系 取名来自明亮的星带
Our Milky Way, so named for its shimmering band of sparkling stars...
将面目全非
will be unrecognizable.
昏暗的恒星躯壳余火未尽的灰烬
Faint glowing embers of dark stellar husks...
将成为曾经辉煌一时的夜景的残骸
will be all that remain...of what was once a brilliant night vision.
星体都是怎么啦？
What happened to all of the stars?
我们怎么会遭遇如此悲惨的境况的呢？
How did we arrive at such a dismal scenario?
科学判定随着我们宇宙膨胀和年长 它将会冷却
Science decrees that as our universe expands and ages, it will cool.
不可避免 我们知道其未来人生
lnevitably, the future for life as we know it...
将会变得越发充满敌意
will grow ever more hostile.
我们迈进的时代
We are headed for a time...
将会是有朝一日宇宙自身连同其中的生命通通被冻死
when one day the universe itself will freeze to death and all life with it...
那就是法则
and that's a law.
在我们科学家研究宇宙的演化时
When we scientists look at the evolution of the universe...
有批评者说 真是疯了
some critics say, "That's crazy.
我们连预测明天的头条新闻都难以做到
"We can barely predict tomorrow's headlines...
你在这里预言今后几十亿 上百亿年后的事情
"and here you are predicting what's going to be happening..."billions and billions ofyears from now.
你怎么知道的？
"How do you do it?"
在科学家考量未来的工具里
Among the tools available to scientists pondering the future...
有古老的热力学定律
are the venerable laws of thermodynamics.
其第一定律称质量和能量的总值是守恒的
The first law says that total matter and energy are conserved.
换言之 你无法无中生有
ln otherwords, you can't get something for nothing.
没有免费的午餐
There's no free lunch.
因此 结果就是一个系统里的物质和能量总量
So it turns out that the total amount of matter and energy in a system...
是既不能被创造也不能被毁灭
can be neither created nor destroyed.
物质和能量可以改变形式
The matter and energy can change forms...
可以相互转换
and they can turn into one another...
然而总量不变
but the total remains the same.
举个例子 在这张卷起的报纸里
So, for example, in this rolled-up newspaper...
有大量的能量储存在报纸的化学键里
there's a lot of energy stored in the chemical bonds of the paper...
但是一旦我点燃报纸
but if l ignite the paper...
我就可以激活这些化学键 开始破坏它们
l can activate those bonds, and l can start breaking them...
以光和热的形式释放出能量
and that releases energy in the form of light and heat...
你可以看到和感觉到
which you can see and feel.
总能量依然没变
The total energy content is still the same...
但是它消散进了空间
but it's being dissipated out into space.
大量的微粒物质散发了 烟散发了
And a lot of particulate matter goes off as well and smoke goes off...
但是如果我将所有的烟雾 微粒物质
but if l were to add up...all the smoke and the particulate matter...
释放的所有能量以及所有东西加在一起
and all the energy that's given off and everything total...
我就会得到和一开始完全相同的质量和能量的总量
I would get exactly the same amount...of mass and energy total as l had to begin with.
它们只是改变了形式
They simply changed forms.
如果质量和能量的总和保持不变
lf the total amount of mass and energy remain constant...
这似乎就意味着宇宙
this seems to imply the universe...
将永远具有能量 应该永续长存
will always have energy and should last forever.
但是热力学第二定律打破了这种说法
But the second law of thermodynamics...crushes this notion.
热力学第二定律是最奇妙的
The second law of thermodynamics...is the most curious of all.
它说无序 即熵的总量
lt says that total amount of disorder or entropy...
在宇宙间总是在提高
always increases in the universe.
换言之 物体生锈 物体衰败
ln otherwords, things rust, things decay...
物体老化 最终分化瓦解
everything gets old and eventually falls apart and rots.
某种意义上说 第二定律就是死刑执行令
ln some sense, the second law is a death warrant...
是宇宙的死刑执行令
a death warrant for the universe.
第二定律声称无一能幸免
The second law says all things must pass.
宇宙间取之不尽的能量
The ever-present supply of energy in the universe...
不可避免的变得更加分散
inevitably becomes more dispersed...
更加无序 更加无用
more chaotic, and more unusable.
天上每一颗燃烧的星星
Each star burning in the sky...
就像这里的每一块木炭
just like each briquette of this charcoal...
终有一天面对厄运
must one day face its fate.
这块木炭是燃料
This piece of charcoal is fuel.
大量的能量浓缩在这小小的木炭里
It has a lot of energy...concentrated into this small, little packet here.
来自木炭里化学键的能量
That energy goes from being in the chemical bonds...of the charcoal briquette...
会以光和热的形式释放出来
to being liberated in the form of heat and light.
恒星上的情况一模一样
Now, a star does a similar thing.
它不是化学意义上的燃烧
lt doesn't burn in a chemical sense.
而是 恒星上烧的是核能
lnstead, in a star, it's nuclear energy.
原子核被压在一起
The nuclei of atoms are being forced together...
聚合产生新的原子核
fusing them, creating new nuclei...
在此过程中将部分物质
and, in the process, transforming some of that matter...
部分质量转换成我们能看到 能感觉到的辐射能
some of that mass, into the radiated energy that we see and we feel.
同样的进程还在宇宙中的活跃的恒星上继续
And the same process is going on...in all the active stars in the universe.
现在 随着这块木炭的燃烧 燃料正逐渐耗尽
Now, as this charcoal is burning, the fuel is getting used up...
你可以看得一清二楚
and you can actually see that.
其颜色正在变成灰
lt's turning into a gray color.
正在变成灰烬
lt's turning into ashes.
同样道理 恒星在耗尽自己的燃料
ln a similarway, stars use up theirfuel.
它们将氢聚合成氦 这样 随着时间的推移
They fuse hydrogen into helium, and so, with time...
氢燃料将变得越来越少
there's less and less hydrogen to fuse.
灰烬中的能量很少
And the ashes have less energy content...
因而 要么难以燃烧
and, thus, are either harder to burn...
要么燃烧时释放很少的能量
or release less energy during the burning process.
这就是我们的太阳的最终结局
This is the eventual fate of our own Sun.
随着年长 它会膨胀和升温
As it ages, it bloats and heats.
地球会烤成炸土豆片
The Earth will be fried to a crisp.
海洋沸腾 动植物通通完蛋
Oceans will boil away, all plants and animals will die...
岩石气化
rocks will start vaporizing...
因为太阳会发出强烈的阳光 剧烈的能量
because the Sun will be producing so much light, so much energy.
那对地球可谓是万世之劫
That'll be a pretty gruesome death for the Earth.
纵观宇宙 太阳之类的恒星
All through the universe, stars that are like the Sun...
都将面临我们太阳所面临的下场
are going to be facing the same challenges...that our own starwill face.
它们在耗尽燃料 它们在膨胀
They're running out offuel, they're swelling up...
它们在对围绕自己的行星制造麻烦
and they're causing problems for the planets that orbit them.
所以不难想象许多地方
So it's not hard to imagine that there are many locations...
生命曾经进化和繁育的地方
where life has evolved and flourished...
现在正在步入死亡
and is now being extinguished.
正如所有的恒星遭遇熵的影响
Just as each star suffers the effects of entropy...
宇宙的其它地方也难逃厄运
so, too, will the rest of the universe.
然而恒星自然而然会通过散发光和热
But stars naturally increase the entropy of the universe...
来增加宇宙的熵
by giving off light and heat...
就像这木炭燃烧的火
just like this fire of burning charcoal...
在自然而然地增加宇宙的熵一样
naturally increases the entropy of the universe.
眼下我们正处于宇宙的一个稳定期
Right nowwe're kind of in a steady period in the universe...
恒星诞生 度过星生 消亡
where stars are born, live out their lives, die...
留下部分气体给下一代
give some of that gas back to the next generation...
又有了新一代的恒星
and you have another generation of stars.
不过恒星形成的速度会随时间逐步减缓
But that rate of star formation is gradually decreasing with time.
随着恒星的燃料的耗尽
And as stars use up theirfuel and burn out...
将没有足够的新恒星形成 来替代它们
there aren't enough new stars being formed to replace them.
但是 此刻我们耗尽了形成新恒星的气体
But the moment we run out of gas to make new stars...
这意味着 对于在册排队的每一颗死亡之星来说
it means for every dead star in the rolls, in the ranks...
并没有替代之星
there's not a star to replace it.
因此 那就是有朝一日的糟糕情况
And so that's a bad situation to be in...the day that happens.
所以 实际上 星系 恒星的巨大集合体
So, effectively, galaxies, giant collections of stars...
普遍会随着时间逐渐暗淡下去
are growing progressively dimmerwith time on average.
最后 当宇宙到了100万亿岁以后
And, eventually, when the universe...is something like a hundred trillion years old...
将基本上不再有闪烁的星星了
there will be essentially no stars still shining.
宇宙将变得极其寒冷 极其黑暗
The universe will be cold and dark indeed.
任何依赖阳光的生命将迅速灭绝
Any life that depends on sunlight will rapidly go extinct...
因为宇宙在衰老
as the universe continues to age...
来自母星的维持生命的能源也越来越少
and as there are fewer and fewer sources of life-providing energy...from a host star.
你可能会觉得恒星个头最大
You might think the most massive stars...
携带的燃料最多 持续的时间也会最长
the ones with the most fuel, will last the longest.
其实 恒星携带的燃料越多
ln reality, the more fuel a star carries...
其燃烧的速度也越快
the faster it burns through it.
宇宙中最后一抹阳光
The final rays of sunlight left in the universe...
将来自所谓的红矮星
will come from stars known as red dwarfs.
这些微型恒星
These miniature stars...
质量比我们太阳小10倍
ten times less massive than our own sun...
温度会低数千度
burn thousands of degrees cooler.
红矮星非常吝啬自己的燃料消耗
Red dwarf stars are much more miserly...
因而 尽管其一开始的燃料就不多
with theirfuel consumption...and so, even though they have less fuel to begin with...
但是 它们持续的时间比我们的太阳长得多
they last much, much longer than our Sun will last.
典型的红矮星可以存活万亿年
A typical red dwarf can live for as long as 14 trillion years.
比我们现在的宇宙年龄要长上1000倍
That's a thousand times longer than the current age of our universe.
但是最终 这些吝啬的小太阳也免不了一死
Eventually, though, even these stingy little suns...will begin to die off.
所以到了我们银河系几十万亿岁时
So when our Milky Way galaxy is tens of trillions ofyears old...
就只有少量的红矮星在那里苟延残喘
and there's only a few red dwarfs remaining...
你可以想象一息尚存的文明
you might imagine that any surviving civilizations...
会意识到末日的来临
will realize that the end is nigh...
他们会簇拥在这几个能源周围
and they will start crowding around these few sources of energy...
竭力掏空以求生存
trying to scrape out an existence.
红矮星可能是广袤 荒芜的宇宙中的生命绿洲
Red dwarfs could be oases of life...in the vast, inhospitable desert of the universe.
然而 对于需要大量热和能量的行星来说
But for a planet to receive as much heat and energy...
从红矮星那里获得和地球从太阳获得的一样多的话
from its red dwarf host as our Earth does from the Sun...
就需要靠得很近
it would need to orbit so closely...
其一年只相当于6个地球日
that one full year would lastjust six Earth days.
天空要比地球这里的蓝天红上好多
The sky would be much more sort ofwhitish red...than our blue skies here on Earth...
因为红矮星发出的蓝光少的可怜
because the red dwarf puts out so little blue light...
你无法看到我们这里看到的蓝天
you wouldn't be able to have the kind of nice blue skies...that we have here now.
但是 宇宙间已经没有更热 更亮的东西了
However, nothing left in the universe would be hotter or brighter.
所以我们银河系终有一朝
So, there will be a time in our galaxy...
只有几颗红矮星还在发光
when there'sjust a few red dwarfs still glowing...
或许就只有那么三两颗在眨着眼睛
and maybejust then three and two and one as they blink out.
天哪 当只有一颗红矮星的时候
And, gosh, when there's one red dwarf left...
假设我呆在围绕着它的行星上
and suppose l'm on the planet circling it...
我会想 噢 天哪
l'll think, "Man, oh, man...
宇宙是个多么寂寞的地方啊
'what a lonely place the universe is.
它的未来惨不忍睹
"What a depressing future it holds."
最后一颗红矮星不复存在后又将如何呢？
What happens after the last red dwarf blinks out of existence?
21世纪的地球生命生机勃勃
Life in the 21st century on Earth thrives within a universe...
生活在大爆炸以后 已经存在了140亿年的宇宙间
that has existed for about14 billion years...since the spark of the Big Bang.
不过在宇宙的宏伟规划里 那简直就是弹指一挥间
But that's no time at all in the grand scheme of the cosmos.
要是宇宙相对人的寿命
lf the universe is comparable to a human life span...
我们还处于宇宙的襁褓期
we are still in the infancy of the universe.
领悟过去以及未来的时光让人头大不已
Getting a grasp of the time that has already elapsed...and the time span still to come can boggle the mind.
为了获得宇宙时间尺度的远景
To gain a perspective of the vast time scales of the universe...
让我们来把宇宙的140亿年历史
let's compress the roughly 14-billion-year history of the universe...
压缩成一个普通的日历
into one normal calendaryear.
不过我们会将其称为宇宙日历
But we'll call this a cosmic calendar.
这样大爆炸发生在元旦 1月1日
So the Big Bang occurred on NewYear's, January1st.
在日历牌上 我们银河系形成于1月末
On that scale, our Milky Way galaxy formed near the end of January...
我们的太阳系大约形成于8月初
and our solar system formed around the beginning ofAugust or so...
一年过去了三分之二
about two-thirds of the way through the year.
生命出现在8月晚些的某个时间
Life formed sometime a little bit later in August...
不过人类出现还不到一天时间
but humans formed less than a day ago.
所以 在12月31日的某个时间 人类终于出现了
So, on December 31st sometime, humans finally arose.
我们同样可以展望未来
We can also look into the future...
就利用同一个宇宙日历的时间尺度
on the same cosmic calendar time scale.
在来年的1月底
Near the end of January of this coming year...
我们的地球变得相当不友好
our Earth will become quite inhospitable.
到了5月前后 我们的太阳行将死亡
By around May or so, our Sun will have died...
不过还有其它一些恒星 低质量的恒星
but there are some other stars, the low-mass stars...
会存活得很长 很长
which will live for much, much longer...
活过这样的宇宙年1万岁
up to10,000 of these cosmic years.
那比整个宇宙历史长出了1万倍
That's 10,000 times longer than the entire history of the universe...
然后那些最长命的红矮星才会退出历史舞台
before these final longest-living red dwarf stars die off.
那么接下来是怎么个情形呢？
But then what happens?
在我们讨论极其遥远的未来时
When we talk about the extremely distant future...
讨论的是极大的时间跨度
we're talking about immense spans of time...
时间以千万亿年计
time measured in quadrillions ofyears...
万万亿年计
and septillions ofyears...
已经变得不知所措了
and it becomes so overwhelming...
我们需要发展另外的概念来处理它了
that we need to evolve another concept to really deal with it.
所以我们就提出了宇宙年代的概念
So we came up with the idea of cosmological decades.
宇宙年代 就是每一个年代
A cosmological decade, each decade is ten times longer...
都是先前从开始以来的整个时段的十倍
than all the time that happened prior to the start ofthe decade.
理解它的一个方法就是它好比台阶
And one way to think about this is that it's like a staircase.
并非像原来的这个台阶
Not an ordinary staircase like this one...
而是每一级台阶都是前面台阶的10倍高
but one in which each step is ten times higher...than the step before.
这样你可以想象台阶一级一级往上增高
So you can imagine the staircase going up and up and up...
宇宙年代就越来越增大
to higher and higher cosmological decades.
目前 我们正处于宇宙10年代
Right now, we're living in the tenth cosmological decade.
按照这个尺度 宇宙10年代
On this scale, the tenth cosmological decade...
就是10倍于大爆炸以来9个年代的总和
is ten times longer than the previous nine decades combined...that have passed since the Big Bang.
宇宙10年代的标志
The hallmark of the tenth cosmological decade...
事实上就是恒星在夜空灿烂闪烁
is the fact that stars are burning brightly in the night sky...
同时行星的表面开始孕育生命和智能
and also that the planets are beginning to develop...life and intelligence on their surfaces.
宇宙10年代另一个有趣的标志
Another interesting hallmark of the tenth cosmological decade...
就是宇宙的膨胀开始加速
is the beginning of the acceleration...of the expansion ofthe universe.
随着我们的宇宙年代的延续
As our cosmological decade continues...
所有的其它星系将淡出视野
all of the other galaxies disappearfrom view...
恒星如果后继乏星的话 将开始步入死亡
and stars begin to die off without being replaced.
到了这个时期的末期 随之都会有约50颗恒星
During the latter part of this era, there will always be about fifty stars...
在星系里闪烁
shining in the galaxy at any one time.
那将会是世界啊 行星啊
And that will be the last sort of gasp...of the kind of world, the kind of planets...
我们熟悉的环境之类的最后的抽气
the kind of environments that are familiar to us.
随着我们经过随后的若干个宇宙年代
As we move through the succeeding cosmological decades...
随着最后的恒星的消亡 我们将步入一个全新的外星纪元
and after the last star dies, we enter a new alien age.
所以到了这里 我们处于宇宙年代20年代到30年代之间
So up here, we're in the cosmological decade 20 through 30...
如果我们环视夜空
and ifwe look out at the night sky...
整个漆黑一团
it's absolutely, utterly, completely black.
不过要是我们能够透过人眼
But ifwe're able to look in light...
都看不透的深红光看出去
that's far too red for the human eye to see...
那么我们实际上会看到天上点缀着死去的恒星
then we'd actually see that the sky is speckled with dead stars.
那就是退化时期
This is the Degenerate Era.
在退化时期里
ln the Degenerate Era...
最大的死亡之星都塌缩成了黑洞
the most massive dead stars have collapsed into black holes.
但是点缀在整个黑暗太空里
But punctuating the total blackness of space...
过去灿烂恒星的余烬还在消耗着最后的能量
the leftover ashes of once bright stars are still ebbing energy.
这些灰烬叫做白矮星
These ashes are called a white dwarf.
它们确实很怪异
Now, they're really weird...
因为你看到的是太阳质量的一半
because you've got something like halfthe mass of our Sun...
也就是地球质量的16万倍
roughly160,000 times the mass of our Earth...
就压缩成了地球那么大的体积
compressed into a volume just the size ofthe Earth.
所以它是非常致密的东西
So it's very dense stuff.
真是怪异的灰烬 毫无疑问
lt's weird ashes, that's for sure.
所以它就好像是余火未尽
So it'll be like the dying ember after a fire.
它已经不可能通过核反应来产生新的能量
lt'll be generating no new energy of its own through nuclearfusion.
不过随着白矮星余烬的熄灭
But as the dying embers of a white dwarf cool...
依然会发出大量的能量
they still emit many megawatts of power.
但是其能量将比现在的太阳产生的
But that is vastly billions, trillions of times less energy...
少数十亿倍乃至数万亿倍
than the Sun is producing right now.
因此要是我们认为我们现在面临了能源危机的话
And so ifwe think we have an energy crisis now...
那么 退化时期的能源危机
the energy crisis in the Degenerate Era...
将会更为严峻 更为严重
will be far more severe and far more profound.
即便如此 这些年迈的恒星残骸所产生的能量
Even so, the energy emanating from these ancient star remnants...
依然大大超过了当代人类文明所消耗的所有能量
is still greater than that consumed today...by all human civilization.
我们来想象一下 要是人类文明
lfwe were to imagine that somehow a human civilization...
延续到了退化时代
were to persist into the Degenerate Era...
他们有可能会利用白矮星所产生的能量
they might be tapping the energy that's emerging from the white dwarf.
不过 人类无法在其表面建立能源采集基地
However, humans wouldn't be able to establish...an energy-gathering outpost on its surface...
一如石油钻井平台固定在海底那样
such as an oil rig anchored to the ocean floor.
其表面的引力大的惊人
Surface gravity is incredibly strong.
你基本上会被碾得粉碎
You would basically be crushed...
如果你企图踏足白矮星的话
ifyou tried to stand on the surface of a white dwarf.
为了生存 未来的文明
To survive, future civilizations...
将需要建立一个轨道殖民地
would need to establish an orbiting colony.
他们会攫取白矮星发出的能量
They would probably tap that energy that's coming from the white dwarf...
通过将某种吸收板
by having some sort of absorbing panels...
同样围绕着白矮星
that are also in orbit around the white dwarf.
这样 自下而上产生的能量
So the energy that's emanating up from below...
将被捕获利用
would be captured and trapped and used.
不过 未来这个白矮星轨道器发出的光
Still, light in this white dwarf-orbiting future...
必须是人工发生的
would have to be generated artificially.
天上并没有星光闪烁
There's no stars shining in the sky.
没有月光
There's no moonlight.
没有阳光
There's no sunlight.
你只是围绕着一个巨大的死气腾腾的暗物质
You're simply orbiting a gigantic, dead black mass.
不幸的是 死气腾腾的暗物质将在退化时期
Unfortunately, dead black masses will make up the bulk of galaxies...
构成星系的主体
during the Degenerate Era.
所以 我们一旦进入退化时代
So, as we go into the Degenerate Era...
将会看到有上千亿颗死亡之星
we'll have roughly a hundred billion dead stars...
在一个巨大的椭圆体里相互环绕
orbiting each other in a giant elliptical configuration.
偶尔 它们会相互作用
Occasionally, they'll interact with one another...
其中会有被逐出星系
and one will get flung out ofthe galaxy...
导致星系丧失质量
causing the galaxy to lose mass.
星系 从某种意义上说 将会慢慢地蒸发
The galaxy, in a sense, will evaporate slowly with time...
伴随着这些东西的抛出
as these things are flung out.
白矮星以及残留的星际物质会掉入黑洞
White dwarfs and remaining galactic material...fall prey to black holes.
日积月累 结果会是
So gradually, with time, what will happen...
星系拥有的物质越来越少
is the galaxy will have fewer and fewer objects in it...
越来越多的部分将会变成黑洞
and a greater and greater fraction of them will be black holes.
什么都逃不脱自宇宙衰老开始
And whatever isn't seized...
就游走其中的无数黑洞的魔爪
by the millions of black holes roaming the universe...begins to decay with old age.
这是另一个一般过程的例子
And this is another example of the general process...
在此过程中 宇宙间的熵的总量有增无减
by which the total amount of randomness increases in the universe.
热力学第二定律再次发挥了作用
The second law of thermodynamics is once again at work.
所有的结构 所有的恒星
And all the structures, all the stars...
基本上消失殆尽了
are basically evaporating into nothing...
所以到了宇宙年代40年代左右
and so by about cosmological decade forty...
构建行星 恒星的大部分物质将完全消失
most of the stuff that's been built...the planets and the stars, are all gone...
退化时期 已经持续了很长时间了
and the Degenerate Era...which has stretched for huge amounts of time...
将告结束
is coming to an end.
障碍通通扫清
With nothing left in theirway...
黑洞统治宇宙的地位固若金汤
black holes stand poised to rule the universe.
这可能就是宇宙残酷的未来
This may be the grim future ofthe cosmos.
行星衰败解体
The planets decay and dissolve...
暗星际残骸散落膨胀的宇宙间
dark galactic remnants scatter across a bloated universe...
甚至连光都成了模糊 遥远的回忆
and even light isjust a faint, distant memory.
随着我们穿越深邃的时间
As we continue through the vast stretches of time...
度量宇宙年代
measured in cosmological decades...
巨大的黑洞幸存了下来成为了我们曾经星光灿烂的夜空中
massive black holes survive as the only recognizable features...
唯一能识别的特征
of our once brilliant night sky.
我们来到了宇宙年代60年代前后
We're up to about cosmological decade sixty-something...
那时你仰望夜空
and when you look out at the night sky...
它出奇的冷 出奇的黑
it's incredibly cold, it's incredibly black...
只有最微弱的电波噼啪作响
and there's only the faintest crackle of radio waves...
引力辐射 回荡在空无一物的空中
and gravitational radiation, echoing through the empty skies.
到了黑洞时期了
This is the Black Hole Era.
宇宙的持续膨胀使其元气大伤
The continuous expansion of the universe has taken its toll.
极度寒冷消耗能量 减缓进程
The unimaginable cold saps energy and constricts movement.
时间本身好像已失去意义
Time itself seems to lose meaning.
到了黑洞时期中期 甚至退化时期
ln the midst of the Black Hole Era, even the Degenerate Era...
仿佛处在了大爆炸后的时间起点上
looks like the first sliver of time after the Big Bang.
在这种环境中 生命还有机会吗？
Does life have a chance in this environment?
人类那时将不复存在 因为质子都不存在了
Humans won't exist at that time because protons won't exist...
但是可以设想有些实体
but it's possible to imagine some kind of entity...
以极其缓慢的速度存活着
which is living at an extraordinarily slow rate.
如果生活缓慢的足够
lf it lives slowly enough...
也许会出现奇怪的生命
perhaps strange life could emerge.
一个念头要用上数万亿年
A thought would take trillions ofyears.
你也许需要用上万亿年来决定午餐
lt may take a trillion years for you to decide what to have for lunch...
因为一切都极其缓慢 一切都近乎绝对零
because everything is so slow, everything is near absolute zero.
黑洞时期的爬行时间尺度
The creeping time scale ofthe Black Hole Era...
可以比作植物的成长
can be compared to the growth ofvegetation.
从人类的角度出发 有关分 小时 天
From a human perspective, involving minutes, hours, and days...
植物的生命似乎是时间的冻结
plant life can seem frozen in time.
根本没什么发生似的
Absolutely nothing seems to be happening.
它似乎完全没有生机 完全静止不动
lt appears to be completely dead, completely static.
但是我们一旦加快时钟 就会看到它的活动
But ifwe speed up the clock, then we see the activity.
植物的生长
The plant grows...
植物活动叶子对阳光作出反应
the plant moves its leaves in response to where the Sun is...
植物在不断活动 不停地干活
the plant is continuously in motion, it's continuously doing things...
但是其生存的尺度 就是时帧要长于
but that whole scale of existence is on a time frame that's longer...
我们通常的体验
than what our experience is used to dealing with.
黑洞时期地盘之争发生在两个黑洞狭路相逢时
The real action in the Black Hole Era occurs...when two black holes meet.
尽管肉眼看不到这两个猛兽的碰撞
Although invisible to human eyes, a collision between these two beasts...
但是会通过时空发出颤动
sends a shudder through space-time.
这种事件可以想象成在一汪静水之间
This event can be imagined in a sheet of perfectly still, calm water.
就好像在静水中突然投下一块大石头
lt's a bit like suddenly dropping a gigantic rock into that calm water...
散开一系列涟漪
sending out a huge series of ripples...
你在一小段时间里看到很多活动
and you have a lot of action for a little bit oftime...
然而随后就消失了 涟漪消失了
but then that dissipates, the ripples die away...
你又回到了平静如镜的水面
and you're back to that smooth, glass-like sheet ofwater.
不过对于这些黑洞时期的霸王而言
But even for these kings of the Black Hole Era...
时间也正在消失
time is running out.
你或许会想 噢 它们会万寿无疆的
And you might think, "Oh, they'll last forever"...
但是它们绝不会万寿无疆的
but even they don't last forever...
因为 它们会随着时间极其缓慢地消失的
because they evaporate very, very slowly with time.
今天宇宙间的黑洞
Black holes in today's universe...
随着吞噬周围的物质而愈长愈大
grow larger as they gobble up surrounding matter.
不过到了最终 遥远的未来
But eventually, far in the future...
吞噬的物质少的可怜
there'll be so little material to swallow...
消亡的速度将开始占上风
that the evaporation rate will start dominating...
胜过它们吞噬周围物质的速度
over the rate at which they swallow material from their surroundings.
所以消亡的速度将越来越快
So the evaporation rate proceeds more quickly...
伴随着宇宙越来越衰老
when the universe is very, very old.
消失中的黑洞是不会发出哀鸣的
An evaporating black hole does not go out with a whimper...
就像行星在临终前那样
like the planets do when they die...
而是发出一声巨响
but ratherwith a bang.
那是因为 当其耗尽燃料时 行为有些不可理喻
That's because it behaves counterintuitively...as it runs out offuel.
基本上有两种策略可供你选择
There's basically two strategies that you can adopt.
其一就是放松油门
One is to sort of ease up on the gas pedal...
尽量保存你的能源
and try to conserve your energy...
忍气吞声努力开到下面的加油站
and basically try to roll into the next gas station on fumes.
另一个策略就有点急躁了
The other strategy is to become impatient...
猛踩油门
and floor the accelerator...
尽可能快地驱车到加油站
and try to drive to the gas station as fast as you can...
希望在燃油耗尽前 赶到加油站
in hopes of getting to the gas station...before your gas runs out.
黑洞绝对是走了第二条路线
And the black holes are definitely taking the second route.
不同于汽车 黑洞在耗尽燃料时就会爆发
Unlike a car, when a black hole finally runs out offuel, it explodes.
在黑洞的最后时刻
And in the last second of the black hole...
你会看到释放出数以万亿吨TNT当量
when you're releasing...megatons and megatons worth of TNT equivalent...
种类繁多的粒子
a huge variety of particles...
那是多少宇宙年代里所从未见到过的
that haven't been seen for many cosmological decades...
喷发进宇宙 如烟花爆裂昙花一现
comes spewing into existence and kind offlicker away...
紧随着黑洞的消亡
in a last fireworks-like burst after the black hole is gone.
经过无数年后
So after about a google years or so...
大部分超大质量的黑洞已经消失殆尽
and the most super-massive black holes have evaporated away...
你最后留下的广袤的宇宙
what you've got left is a vast universe...
真的是几乎整个一片真空
that is really almost entirely empty.
接下来 宇宙进入了黑暗时期
Next, the universe enters the Dark Era.
现在我们的宇宙已经过了宇宙年代100年代
Nowwe're out beyond cosmological decade 100.
我们来到了黑暗时期中期
We're in the middle of the Dark Era.
到了黑暗时期 我们现在所见的一切
ln the Dark Era, everything that we have now...
全都不是我们所熟悉的
that is familiar to us is gone.
你知道成语"天使避之三舍"吗？
You know that expression, "angels fear to tread"?
那就是黑暗时期
That's the Dark Era.
黑暗时期 你永远都不会想去的
The Dark Era, you neverwant to go to...
因为一切都崩溃了
because everything has crumbled...
不光是人们冒失闯入的沙漠与古迹
notjust the sands and monuments to man's folly...
甚至连原子本身都崩溃了
but even the atoms themselves have begun to crumble.
甚至黑洞在黑暗时期都无容身之地
Even black holes are not possible in the dark era.
如果宇宙无休止地一直膨胀下去
lf the universe continues to expand forever...
就有可能只有一大团随机粒子残留着
it may be that only a cosmic mush of random particles remains...
不过还是有一些惊喜冒出这些余烬
but a few surprises may yet rise out ofthese ashes.
要是在遥远的未来 混乱一统天下
lf, in the distant future, chaos does rule over order...
我们曾经炙热的宇宙将会陷入
our once glowing-hot universe will descend...
可怕的星系冰河时期
into a chilling galactic ice age.
但是它依然会存在某种潜在的庇护所
But it may still harbor some potential...
至少根据量子理论
at least according to quantum theory...
这种从最原始层面研究物理学的理论
which examines physics at its most primal level.
在量子理论中 即使在真空中
ln quantum physics, even the vacuum of space...
我们认为其中一无所有
that thing that we think of as being empty with nothing in it...
其实并非是空无一物
is not actually empty.
量子理论承认一切情况皆有可能
Quantum physics allows for everything to happen...with some probability.
换言之 宇宙是在豪赌
ln otherwords, the universe is playing a risky game of chance.
量子理论试图解释粒子的行为
And quantum theory seeks to explain the behavior of particles...
在宇宙间 一切皆有可能
in a universe where anything is possible.
仿佛宇宙是个发牌者
lt's as if the universe were a card dealer...
不停地洗牌
continuously shuffling a deck...
掌控着构建我们现实的各种组合
containing the very building blocks of our reality.
因此 如果你拥有一堆量子场理论里的粒子
So if you have a bunch of particles in a quantum field theory...
那么 接下来的就是它们会自己重新排列
what happens is they're going to just rearrange themselves...
反反复复地派给我们
over and over and over again in what looks to us...
就像是波动的随机集
like a random set offluctuations.
量子理论无法预测粒子洗牌的结果
Quantum theory can't predict the result of a particle shuffle...
但是 它可以揭示每个结果的概率
but it can reveal the probability of each outcome.
如果你看到不断发生的情况
lfyou have something that happens forever...
无数次发生
an infinite number of times...
极不可能的情况却会最终发生
even very, very unlikely things will eventually happen.
通常 洗牌时
Ordinarily, when shuffling a deck of cards...
结果是个随机的系列
the result is a random sequence.
同样 粒子在量子层面上搅和
Likewise, particles, churning on a quantum level...
一般不会产生有序的情况
don't usually create anything orderly.
然而 只要有足够的时间
However, with enough time...
任何量子波动都会产生
any kind of quantum fluctuation can form...
看似不可能的结果
even one that seems impossible.
如果你置身永恒的宇宙间
lfyou're in a universe that lasts forever...
如果你看到发牌者在无休止地洗牌
ifyou have a card dealer that is shuffling cards forever and ever...
那种极不可能的事件偶尔也会发生的
even unlikely events like that will occasionally happen.
这些独特 不可能的随机波动之一
One of these unique and improbable random fluctuations...
可以改变空间结构本身
can change the fabric of space itself.
真空就像是水
Empty space is kind of like water...
也就是说 它可以表现出各种状态
in the sense that it can appear in different phases.
它可以受热蒸发
lt could be hot and be vapor...
可以成为冰块状的固体
it could be solid like an ice cube...
或者可以成为液体
or it could be liquid.
我们周围的空间都处于一定的物理状态中
The space around us right now is in a certain physical state...
但是形态可以发生变化
but a phase transition can happen...
也就是其物理状态变成了其它的状态
where that physical state changes into something else.
错误的随机波动
The wrong kind of random fluctuation...
可能引发毁灭性的状态变化
can induce a devastating phase transition.
发生之地将会是空间的某些区域
The way that would occur is that some region of space...
某些点 会看到有泡沫形成
some point, would witness the formation of a bubble...
泡沫会扩散到周围的整个空间
and that bubble would spread throughout the space around it...
就像这个墨水扩散到整个水杯
just like this inkwould spread through the glass.
和墨水改变了水的属性一样
Just as the ink changes the nature of the water...
同样 形态的变化也改变了宇宙的属性
so could a phase transition transform the nature of the cosmos.
这个泡沫扩散的尾波中的物理定律将会各有不同
The laws of physics would be different...in the wake of this bubble passing.
各种粒子的质量将会发生改变
The masses of different particles would change...
各种粒子的电荷将会发生改变
the charge of different particles would change...
我们所知的整个化学性质将会完全不同
all of chemistry as we know it would be completely different...
只要这种形态一旦发生
after this phase transition occurred.
那就意味着 突然之间 有个新的方法
What that means is that suddenly there are newways...
来安排构成我们的粒子
to arrange all the particles that we're made of...
这就好像是宇宙间的一切
and it's sort of like everything in the universe...
都变成了原子弹
becomes an atomic bomb.
它会自我重新安排 释放能量
lt would just rearrange itself, releasing energy...
严格地说 每一个粒子 每一个原子
and literally every particle, every atom...
宇宙间的每一个结构都会爆发
every structure in the universe would explode.
所以复杂的结构无一幸免于这个变化
So no complicated structure can possibly survive that sort of transition.
剩下的只是一派混乱
What would be left isjust a mess...
只有粒子气体在相互随机相撞
nothing but a gas of particles bumping randomly into each other.
但是随机量子波动也可以引发希望的泡沫
But a random quantum fluctuation can also spark a bubble of hope.
有些理论物理学家提出
Some theoretical physicists suggest...
其中的一些量子波动
that some ofthese quantum fluctuations...
实际上可以产生几乎完全隔离的空间
actually can give rise to almost detached portions of space...
从我们宇宙分叉进新的宇宙的维度
dimensions that sort of branch off from ours into a new universe.
或许是量子波动导致了大爆炸
Perhaps a quantum fluctuation sparked the Big Bang...
产生了我们这个宇宙
and gave rise to our own universe.
你可以想象我们这样的宇宙
You can imagine that a universe like ours...
尽管有100亿光年宽
even though it's ten billion light-years across...
其实是个婴儿宇宙
is actually a baby universe that arose...
是从某个大上好多的宇宙收缩而来的
by pinching off from some much bigger universe.
我们可以想象婴儿宇宙诞生于这个瓶子
We can picture the birth of a baby universe...
它代表着一个古老 垂死 混沌的宇宙
with this bottle, representing an old, dying, chaotic universe.
我的吐气就像是量子波动
My breath is like quantum fluctuations...
创造出新的宇宙 样子就像泡沫
creating new universes that look like bubbles.
每一个泡沫都是一个属于自己的独立的宇宙
And each one of those bubbles is a separate universe all of its own.
外面有可能存在着别的宇宙
There is the possibility that there are other universes out there...
或许是从我们宇宙分出去的
perhaps butted off from our universe...
它们或许有自己的结局
and they may have their own fate...
不是无限膨胀 就是最终重新塌缩
either eternal expansion or ultimate re-collapse.
假如有其它宇宙存在 那么或许未来的文明
If other universes exist, then perhaps future civilizations...
就不用面对不可撤消的死刑判决了
may not face an irrevocable death sentence.
因此 我怀疑 今后万亿 千万亿年后
So l would suspect that trillions, quadrillions ofyears from now...
一旦宇宙真的变得很冷时
when the universe gets really cold...
宇宙濒临死亡时
and the universe is near death...
智能生物会变得非常强大
intelligent beings will be so powerful then...
他们或许会努力积聚足够的能量于一点
that they may be tempted to assemble enough energy...
去打开泡沫
at one point to open up bubbles...
小肥皂泡 通往另一个宇宙的关卡
little soap bubbles, gateways to another universe...
那里有很多温暖 他们可以从头再来
where it's a lot warmer and they can start all over again.
不管我们的子孙后代
Whether or not our descendants...
如何积聚技术离开这个宇宙
muster the technology to leave this universe...
都无法回避那样的事实
there's no avoiding the fact that...
就是和所有的东西一样 终将告别历史舞台
like all things, it will come to an end.
虽然 科学界挣扎于宇宙如何消亡的问题
While science wrestles with questions of how the universe will die...
但是 人类同样要做的就是如何生存下去
humanity is left to do the same with how it will live.
我们的生活要紧
Our lives are important.
我要紧 你要紧
l'm important, you're important...
你所爱之人要紧 你的朋友要紧
your loved ones are important, yourfriends are important...
我们要抓住短暂人生 活出潇洒精彩
and we need to make the most of our existence...during the fleeting time that we have here.
这就是你的人生 这就是我的人生
This is your life, this is my life.
我们要把握人生 何虑宇宙的命运
We make the most of it, regardless of the fate of the universe.
谢谢观赏
Thanks For Viewing